<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>AllThatIsOKBut</title><link href="https://souravdatta.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://souravdatta.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://souravdatta.github.io/</id><updated>2019-07-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>The Naive Philospher asks "what is living"?</title><link href="https://souravdatta.github.io/the-naive-philospher-asks-what-is-living.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-30T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-07-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Sourav Datta</name></author><id>tag:souravdatta.github.io,2019-07-30:/the-naive-philospher-asks-what-is-living.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h6&gt;In the beginning there was a question&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was playing with my 3yo kid the other day, or at least was pretending to play 
while scrolling endlessly in some app in my phone, when something happened. 
He asked me a question -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: Why is this rabbit not taking care …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h6&gt;In the beginning there was a question&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was playing with my 3yo kid the other day, or at least was pretending to play 
while scrolling endlessly in some app in my phone, when something happened. 
He asked me a question -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: Why is this rabbit not taking care of itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: What? Which rabbit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: That toy rabbit over there. See, it has a spot on its eye!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: Oh that! That's a toy, must of fell down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: But it should have taken care of itself, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: How can a toy take care of itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: Why not? We all should take care of ourselves, like you said!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: Well, yeah! But a toy is not a living thing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: Then what is a living thing? Are we living? Or are we toys too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, that's the kind of questions that goes &lt;em&gt;"TRRRIINGGGG!"&lt;/em&gt; in my head these days since that 
enlightened morning when I decided to take the &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to Philosophy&lt;/strong&gt; course on Coursera. 
So I immediately launched a Plato style dialogue in my head with an imaginary kid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not always very easy or convenient to launch a Plato
in your head, because you have stuffs to do with real human beings - like shopping or picking up people from shopping - 
and failing to do so often causes real anxieties that may lead to even deeper
philosophical questions like "Why is living?"  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to dialectics now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;Next there were some dialogues&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: So what then, father, is living? How do I know that it is a toy
and not an object which is alive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: Indeed that is a great question! Come to think of it, the first thing
that comes to me - a property of living objects - is to be able to move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: But father, my toy robot moves too. Does it mean it is alive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: No, of course not. It does not move out of its own volition. Rather it
moves because you make it so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: So, moving on its own makes it alive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: Possibly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: Then father, is it the movement of alive things make it alive or
just the ability to do so? Remember when my old grandfather was bed ridden
for several days and he could move at all, not without help from others. 
Event if he wanted to move on his own, he could not. But he was still alive,
wasn't he?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: Yes, you are right. However, it was only temporarily that he could not
move. His internal organs were functioning as is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kid&lt;/em&gt;: So may be movement isn't a necessary property of aliveness? May be
something deeper - something to do with the organs of a being?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;: Perhaps you are right. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>